"Does Resveratrol Benefit Our Metabolic Health?"
To see if the amount
of resveratrol you get
from drinking red wine
might be beneficial,
researchers looked to
the Chianti region of Tuscany
to determine whether the levels
achieved through diet
help protect
against long-term frailty,
inflammation,
cardiovascular disease,
cancer, or death.
And the answer?
None of the above.
The amount of resveratrol
flowing through their systems
didn't correlate with any
of the health outcomes studied
over nine years of follow-up.
This is surprising
even if only because of
the confounding factors
associated
with wine consumption.
Wine drinkers may be
less likely to smoke
and tend to have higher IQ,
higher parental
education levels,
and higher
socioeconomic status,
which would be expected
to correlate
with better health outcomes.
In contrast, beer drinkers
suffer the opposite—
lower IQ, parental education,
and social class.
The average IQ
of wine-drinking men is 113,
compared to 95
among beer-drinking men.
Yet still, there appeared
to be no correlation
between resveratrol exposure
and well-being.
This may be because
wine-drinking populations
may only be averaging
less than a milligram
of resveratrol a day.
Some "experts" recommend
a daily dose
of 1 gram of resveratrol,
based on the dosing used
in laboratory animal studies.
How much red wine
would you have to drink
to get that much?
Eight thousand glasses a day.
Not a fan of red wine?
A couple thousand gallons
of white wine a day
would do it,
or 5,000 pounds of apples
or grapes,
50,000 pounds of peanuts,
a couple thousand pounds
of chocolate,
or nearly a million bottles
of beer on the wall.
The natural levels
of resveratrol
found in foods and beverages
is not considered
to be sufficient
to elicit health effects,
but that doesn't
necessarily mean
supplements wouldn't work.
However, the bioavailability
of even high-dose resveratrol
has been called into question.
Maximum blood levels after
resveratrol supplementation
can be as low as 40 nanomolar,
which is more than
a hundred times lower
than the 5,000 to 250,000
nanomoles used in vitro
to demonstrate
resveratrol effects.
Even a five-gram dose
of resveratrol
may fall short
of the required level.
This is in contrast to rodents,
in which blood levels
of 32,000 have been reported.
Resveratrol is rapidly absorbed
in humans
but is rapidly metabolized
in our intestine and liver;
so, very little
free resveratrol remains.
But there are about 20
resveratrol-derived metabolites
that can end up in circulation
at much higher levels,
like 20,000 nanomolar,
that might have biological
activity of their own.
What about using
the turmeric trick
of adding black pepper
to suppress
our body's natural
detoxification mechanisms?
It works in mice.
The black pepper compound
piperine
increases maximum
blood concentrations
of resveratrol
more than 1,000 percent,
but, unfortunately, it failed
to significantly alter
blood levels in people.
In a 2014 medical journal
editorial entitled
"The resveratrol fiasco,"
the Editor-in-Chief summarized
the state of the science:
"The conclusions
are quite clear-cut:
after more than 20 years
of well-funded research,
resveratrol has no proven
human activity."
However,
since that publication,
more than 150
human clinical trials
have been published.
What's the update?
Resveratrol was initially
envisaged as an antioxidant,
but meta-analyses
of randomized controlled trials
of resveratrol supplements
failed to find
clinically or even statistically
significant effects
on systemic markers
of oxidative stress,
helping to explain the lack
of apparent DNA protection.
Maybe it only helps with
the metabolically compromised?
As one resveratrol review asked,
"What conclusions would we draw
about the efficacy
of penicillin
if it had been tested
only among persons
in the pink of condition?"
Resveratrol does not appear
to improve
the metabolic function
of nonobese,
nondiabetic individuals,
or even benefit
overweight nondiabetics,
nor does it help people
lose weight,
but resveratrol may help
with blood sugar control
in diabetics.
For almost all outcomes
measured in randomized
controlled trials
of type 2 diabetes,
metabolic syndrome,
or nonalcoholic
fatty liver disease,
the effects of resveratrol
were trivial,
but a meta-analysis did find
that in doses ranging
from 5 to 500 milligrams
twice a day resulted
in an average 20-point drop
in fasting blood sugars.
There was also
a significant benefit
for longer-term
blood sugar control,
though this only appeared
to be the case
in shorter-term studies.
What is the point
of better longer-term control,
if it only works in studies
lasting less than three months.
Diabetic foot ulcers
are the leading cause
of lower-limb amputations
in diabetics.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of 50 milligrams of resveratrol
twice a day
showed accelerated healing
of diabetic foot ulcers
by about 1 centimeter
over placebo within 60 days.
So, at least there's
one condition it may help.
Next, I'll cover resveratrol
for joint, brain,
and bone health,
and then I'll talk
about the downsides.